<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2005 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors, as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
 -->
<document url="howtobuildsite.xml"><properties>  
	<author email="mike_edwards@uk.ibm.com">Mike Edwards</author>  
	<title>Apache Tuscany - How To Build Site</title></properties><body> 
	 
	<section name="Tuscany Site Generation Overview">
	
		<p>The Tuscany website is built using the site plugin of Maven 2.0.  A general guide to
		the Maven site plugin can be found <a href="http://maven.apache.org/guides/mini/guide-site.html">here</a>.
		</p>
		<p>
		The website is held in the site subproject of Tuscany, with a set of source files in the src/site 
		directory and the final website files held in the target/site directory.  The website project has its own POM
		file, held in the main site directory.
		The site is generated using the command
		<pre>
			mvn site
		</pre>
		from the main site directory, which uses the source files to build the final website files in the target/site
		directory.
		</p>
		<p>
		The actual live website for Tuscany is at 
		<a href="http://incubator.apache.org/tuscany/">http://incubator.apache.org/tuscany/</a>.  The files for the live
		website are transferred from the Tuscany subversion repository to the machine people.apache.org in the directory 
		/www/incubator.apache.org/tuscany, using a subversion extract of the site/target/site directory. So, if you
		update the site/target directory on SVN and want to make the new version live, you will need to logon to
		people.apache.org and type in:
		<pre>
			cd /www/incubator.apache.org/tuscany
			svn update
		</pre>
		</p>
		
	</section>
	<section name="Location and Format of the Source Files">
		
		<p>The source files for the Tuscany site are held in the site/src/site directory.  In that
		directory there is a special file called site.xml which holds the basic layout for all the
		pages in the site.  In particular, site.xml contains the definitions for the left menu bar
		and for the overall title on each page. Only edit site.xml if you need to add a new top
		level page to the site.
		</p>
		<p>
		Most of the pages for the site are held in the xdoc directory.  The pages are generally in
		an XML format, although it is possible to define pages as HTML files.  XML files are 
		preferred, since Maven applies a standard layout and style sheet to these pages.  If you
		provide a page as an HTML file, it will appear exactly as you create it - Maven does not
		modify HTML files as it creates the site.
		</p>
		<p>
		The website landing page is defined by index.xml.  The other pages are linked from this
		page, either via the left sidebar or via explicit links in the body of the page.  The
		following section gives you some details on how to create your own page and link it into
		the site.
		</p>
		<p>
		Other files are held in the resources directory.  These files include things like images
		(eg. JPEG files) and documents (eg. PDF files).  These files can be referenced from the
		pages in the xdocs directory, without the need for any path - Maven copies the files in 
		the resources directory to the root directory of the website.
		</p>
		
	</section>
	<section name="Creating your own Pages">
		<p>
		You can get a good feel for the format of the pages in the Tuscany website by looking at
		some of the existing files in the xdoc directory.  bugs.xml is a good example of a simple
		page with a reference hyperlink.  documentation.xml is an example of a more complex page
		which has a table.  The format of the xml files uses a simple set of elements that
		approximate to the more common HTML tags.  To get a feel for the XML elements, let's use an example
		of creating a new page called foo.xml.
		</p>
		<p>
		First, create a file called foo.xml in the xdocs directory, similar to the following:

		<pre>
		&lt;document url="foo.xml"&gt;
		&lt;properties&gt;  
			&lt;author email="your_id@blah.com"&gt;Your Name&lt;/author&gt;
			&lt;title&gt;Apache Tuscany - Foo&lt;/title&gt;
		&lt;/properties&gt;
		&lt;body&gt;
			&lt;section name="Tuscany Foo"&gt;	
			&lt;p&gt;
			Welcome to the foo section.  
			Please review the &lt;a href="tuscany_foo.pdf"&gt;Tuscany FOO manual&lt;/a&gt;.
			You can run foo by typing in the command:
			&lt;pre&gt;
				foo bar
			&lt;/pre&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt; 

		&lt;/section&gt;
		&lt;/body&gt;
		&lt;/document&gt;
		</pre>
		
		Note the header information with a general title in the properties section - this gets applied to the title line of
		the browser when the page is displayed.  There is a body section, which is the main content
		of the page.  Within the body, each section tag places a heading into the page.  Paragraphs
		are defined using the &lt;p&gt; tags. Hyperlink references can be created using the &lt;a&gt;
		element.  For descriptions of commands and similar text elements, you can use the &lt;pre&gt;
		element.
		</p>
		<p>
		References like "tuscany_foo.pdf" should be dropped into the site/resources directory.  
		</p>
		<p>If the foo page needs to be linked from the left bar, then a link to foo must be created in the
		site.xml file which is in the main src/site directory:

		<pre>
		...
		&lt;menu name="Tuscany"&gt;
		...
		&lt;item name="Foo"  href="foo.html" /&gt;
		&lt;/menu&gt;
		...
		</pre>
		Note that the link here is to foo.html, not to foo.xml - foo.html is the name of the page
		in the final website format.
		</p>
	</section>  

</body>
</document> 