<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2005 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors, as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
 -->
<document url="index.xml">
	<properties>
		<author email="mgmarum@us.ibm.com">Matthew Marum</author>
		<title>Apache Tuscany</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Apache Tuscany">
			<p>
				Welcome to Apache Tuscany. The Apache Tuscany project is currently in Incubation under the 
				Apache Incubator.
			</p>
			<p>Apache Tuscany project simplifies the development of business solutions using a service-oriented architecture (SOA).
                        It provides an implementation for Service Component Architecture (SCA), Service Data Objects (SDO) and Relational Database Data Access Service (RDB DAS)
                         in conjunction with other well-established Java<sup>tm</sup> runtime environments such as Apache Axis, Apache Tomcat, and Apache Geronimo.
			</p>
                        <p>SCA provides developers with a simple model for creating systems based on SOA and addresses infrastructure capabilities such as transactions,
                         security and reliable messaging. Solutions developed using SCA can be declaratively changed to alter infrastructure capabilities or application
                          configuration properties to meet business requirements.
                          For example, security policies or currency for one environment may be different from those required by another environment and SCA allows
                           these to be changed declaratively without the need for re-implementation.  
                        </p>
                        <p>
SCA divides up the steps in building a service-oriented application into two major parts:
<ul>
<li>
The Implementation of components which provide services and consume other services. SCA supports service implementations written using any one of many programming languages, both including conventional object-oriented and procedural languages such as Java<sup>tm</sup>, PHP, C ++,  and also  XML-centric languages such as BPEL and XSLT, and also declarative languages such as SQL and XQuery. SCA also supports a range of programming styles, including asynchronous and message-oriented styles, in addition to the synchronous call-and-return style.
</li>
<li>
The Assembly of sets of components to build composite business applications that addresses specific business requirements. This is performed by wiring together the service implementation components.  
</li>
</ul>
 For more information about SCA read the white paper on Service Component Architecture (SCA) on <a href="documentation.html">Documentation page</a>. Tuscany provides runtime implementation of SCA in both Java and C++.
                        </p>
                        <p>SDO provides a consistent view of data regardless of the type of data store where the data resides. It maintains history of change in data as
                            well as referential integrity of schema. Tuscany implements SDO in Java and C++. 
                            PHP implementation of SDO is also available under PECL at this link <script type="text/javascript">linkNewWindow('http://pecl.php.net/package/sdo','http://pecl.php.net/package/sdo');</script>
                            To further understand the benefits of SDO please refer to the white paper called SDO white paper on the <a href="documentation.html">Documentation page</a>. 
                        </p>
                        <p>
RDB DAS provides a generic data access service that provides transformation capability between SDO data graphs and relational databases and vise versa. To further explore the benefits of DAS please refer to white paper on <a href="documentation.html">Documentation page</a>.  
                        </p>
<p>
You can get a feel for what it's like to create simple applications using Tuscany by trying out the Sample Programs that are supplied with the Tuscany project.
                        </p>
                        <p>
The specifications for SDO and SCA can be found on the <a href="documentation.html">Documentation page</a>:<br/> 
<ul>
<li>
The SCA 0.9 Assembly Model specification 
</li>
<li>
The SCA 0.9 Client and Implementation Model specifications - for Java and for C++ 
</li>
<li>
The SDO 2.01 specifications - for Java and for C++
</li>
</ul>
                        </p>
                        <p>     Tuscany is very interested in getting your comments or any feedback you may have.  Please feel free
                                to post these on the mailing lists.  Mailing list information is available in the <a href="mail-lists.html">Project Mailing Lists</a> section.
                                We look forward to your involvement in Tuscany.  
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Tuscany Subprojects">
			<p>
				Tuscany consists of 5 subprojects, each dealing with different aspects of the SOA programming model:
				<ol>
					<li>SCA Runtime for Java</li>
					<li>SDO 2.0 Runtime for Java</li>
					<li>Data Access Service for Java</li>
					<li>SCA Runtime for C++</li>
					<li>SDO 2.0 Runtime for C++</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="What's New?">
			<p>
				(March 6 2006) The codebase has reached a first stable milestone at SVN revision 383106.
				Both the Java and C++ projects have advanced to provide end-to-end support for a range of
				scenarios.  For the Java project, the codebase now integrates with Apache Tomcat 5.5.15 and Axis 2.0. 
				There is a substantial set of working samples for the SCA, SDO and DAS subprojects, which can run on
				Windows, Linux and Mac.  There is also support for writing service components in Javascript.
			</p>
			<p>
				With this combination you can write service components that provide Web services or that provide 
				business services supporting a Web UI based on Servlets and JSPs.
			</p>
			<p>
				(Jan 10 2006) The current code in the Tuscany
				project is an initial implementation, which is still
				very much evolving. We're looking to add a lot of
				additional function over the coming weeks and months,
				such as support for additional implementation types and
				for additional bindings. We're looking for people to
				help us add these capabilities - so please take some
				time to look over the project and join us in this
				exciting developement.
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
