<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2005 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors, as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
 -->
<document url="index.xml">
	<properties>
		<author email="mgmarum@us.ibm.com">Matthew Marum</author>
		<title>Apache Tuscany</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Apache Tuscany">
			<p>
				Welcome to Apache Tuscany. The Apache Tuscany project is currently in Incubation under the 
				Apache Incubator.
			</p>
			<p>
				Apache Tuscany provides runtime capabilities for applications built 
				using a Service Oriented Architecture (SOA). Tuscany provides capabilities which follow the 
				Service Component Architecture specification and the Service Data Objects specification, which 
				together define a simpler, business-oriented approach to the creation of applications and solutions
				which use a SOA.
			</p>
			<p>
				Currently, Tuscany provides separate runtime support for the Java language and for the C++
				language.  This means that you can write service components in either the Java language or in
				the C++ language.
			</p>
			<p>
				For more information on the SOA programming model provided
				by Tuscany, you can read:
				<ul>
					<li>
						A White Paper on Service Component Architecture
						(SCA)
					</li>
					<li>The SCA 0.9 Assembly Model specification</li>
					<li>
						The SCA 0.9 Client and Implementation Model
						specification
					</li>
					<li>The SDO 2.01 specification</li>
				</ul>
				These are available on the <a href="documentation.html">Documentation</a> page.
				You can also get a feel for what it's like to create a program using Tuscany by trying out the 
				Sample Programs that are supplied with the Tuscany project.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Tuscany Subprojects">
			<p>
				Tuscany consists of 5 subprojects, each dealing with different aspects of the SOA programming model:
				<ol>
					<li>SCA Runtime for Java</li>
					<li>SDO 2.0 Runtime for Java</li>
					<li>Data Access Service for Java</li>
					<li>SCA Runtime for C++</li>
					<li>SDO 2.0 Runtime for C++</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="What's New?">
			<p>
				(March 6 2006) The codebase has reached a first stable milestone at SVN revision 383106.
				Both the Java and C++ projects have advanced to provide end-to-end support for a range of
				scenarios.  For the Java project, the codebase now integrates with Apache Tomcat 5.5.15 and Axis 2.0. 
				There is a substantial set of working samples for the SCA, SDO and DAS subprojects, which can run on
				Windows, Linux and Mac.  There is also support for writing service components in Javascript.
			</p>
			<p>
				With this combination you can write service components that provide Web services or that provide 
				business services supporting a Web UI based on Servlets and JSPs.
			</p>
			<p>
				(Jan 10 2006) The current code in the Tuscany
				project is an initial implementation, which is still
				very much evolving. We're looking to add a lot of
				additional function over the coming weeks and months,
				such as support for additional implementation types and
				for additional bindings. We're looking for people to
				help us add these capabilities - so please take some
				time to look over the project and join us in this
				exciting developement.
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>