<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
       <title>Tuscany DAS</title>
       <bannertitle>Tuscany DAS</bannertitle>
       <author email="luckbr1975@gmail.com">Luciano Resende</author>
       <tab>das</tab>
    </properties>
    <body>

        <section name="Data Access Service - Overview">
			<p>RDB DAS provides robust a generic data access service that provides
			transformation capability between SDO data graphs and relational databases and
			vise versa. </p>
			
			<p>By using RDB DAS, applications developers avoid the details and complications 
			of working directly with a relational database and also the complex transformation 
			between relational rows/columns and Data Object types/properties.
			</p>
			
			<p>RDB DAS works with SDO to improve your data access performance.The RDB DAS 
			processes the SDO change summary and produces efficient update statements 
			that only write to columns that have actually been modified.			
			</p>
			
			
			<p>The following diagram illustrates these two capabilities in
			a typical client interaction.The client
			starts by reading a graph of data specified by some query.The client then makes modifications to the
			graph, possibly by adding elements, and then requests the DAS to push the
			changes back to the database.</p>
			
			<img src ="images/sdo_das_sm.jpg" alt="DAS Capabilities" align="middle" border="0" height="407" width="600"/>
			
			<p>To further explore the benefits of DAS please refer to white
			paper &quot;DAS White Paper: The Data Access Service&quot; on the <a
			href="documentation.html">Documentation
			page</a>.</p>
        </section>

       <section name="General DAS Documentation">
	               <p>Below, there is a list of various links to documents that help to explain various aspects of the
		       Tuscany DAS subproject and the programming model that it provides.  More general documentation 
		       which applies to the Tuscany project as a whole can be found on the
		       <a href="documentation.html">Tuscany Documentation page</a>.
		      </p>
		      
                      <p>
		      <table class="bodyTable">
			 <tr class="b">
			    <td>
			       <span style="font-weight: bold;">Title</span>
			    </td>
			    <td>
			       <span style="font-weight: bold;">Description</span>
			    </td>
			 </tr>

			 <tr class="b">
			    <td>
			       <a href='RDB_DAS_white_paper_v-0.2.pdf' target='_blank'>DAS White Paper: The Data Access Service</a>
			    </td>
			    <td>
			       How to access relational data in terms of Service Data Objects
			    </td>
			 </tr>

			 <tr class="b">
			    <td>
			       <a class="external" rel="nofollow" href='http://java.sys-con.com/read/260053.htm'>JDJ DAS Article</a>
			    </td>
			    <td>
			       How to access relational data in terms of Service Data Objects
			    </td>
			 </tr>	            
		      </table>	    
                      </p>
    </section>

    </body>
</document>
