<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2005 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors, as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
 -->
<document>

    <properties>
       <title>Tuscany Maven Quick Introduction</title>
       <bannertitle>Tuscany Maven Quick Introduction</bannertitle>
    </properties>


        <body>
<section name="Maven Quick Reference">
                        <p>
                                For some help getting started with Maven, look at:
                    <script type="text/javascript">linkNewWindow('http://maven.apache.org/guides/getting-started/index.html','http://maven.apache.org/guides/getting-started/index.html');</script> 
            </p>
             <p>
                    With Maven, there is no build "script" like the ant build.xml file. Instead you 
                                provide Maven with a description of your project and it uses that information to
                                determine how to achieve your build goal. The description is held in a pom.xml file.
                                There is a pom.xml file at the top level of your project and there are subsidiary
                                pom.xml files for modules within your project which are referenced from the top level
                                pom file. The Maven project has also established a set of best practices for
                                structuring builds and if you follow those you can get away with very little 
                                description; the Tuscany builds are set up that way.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                                The general rule for maven is that each (sub)project produces one build artifact 
                                (typically a jar file). You can see this in the java project directory where
                                there are separate projects for sca, sdo, das (etc) and within these, separate
                                folders and pom files for major components such as container.java.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                                The main Maven 2.x command is "mvn" and the default goal is "install" which will 
                                compile, unit test and package each project. This will typically output a
                                jar file that is installed locally so that other projects can depend on it.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           Once you have the Java project setup up, you can build the project by issuing the following command in the tuscany root directory:<br/>
                           <code>
                              mvn
                            </code>
                            
                        </p>
                </section>
        </body>
</document>
