<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
       <title>Tuscany SCA</title>
       <bannertitle>Tuscany SCA</bannertitle>
       <tab>sca</tab>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Service Component Architecture - Overview">
            <p> SCA provides developers with a simple, business-oriented, model for creating systems based on a service oriented 
                architecture. It manages infrastructure complexities such as transactions, security and reliable 
                messaging and frees the developer to focus on providing business function. The solutions developed 
                using SCA can be changed declaratively to alter infrastructure capabilities or application configuration 
                properties to meet changing business requirements. For example, infrastructure capabilities such as 
                security policies may change from one environment to another and can be changed without the need for 
                re-implementation. Application configuration may also be changed in this way, for example, the currency 
                quoted by a stock quote feed may be changed though the SCA configuration mechanism.</p>

           <p> SCA divides up the steps in building a service-oriented application into two major parts:</p>
           <br/>
           <p>* The Implementation of components which provide services and consume other services. SCA supports 
              service implementations written using any one of many programming languages, both including conventional 
              object-oriented and procedural languages such as Javatm, PHP, C ++. XML-centric languages such as BPEL 
              and XSLT, and also declarative languages such as SQL and XQuery. SCA also supports a range of programming
              styles, including asynchronous and message-oriented styles, in addition to the synchronous 
              call-and-return style.</p>
           <p>* The Assembly of sets of components to build composite business applications that addresses specific 
              business requirements. This is performed by wiring together the service implementation components. </p>

           <div align="center">
		   <br/>
		   Click on the diagram for more information.
		   <br/><br/>
           <img src ="images/SCAComposite.png" alt="SCA Composite" usemap ="#scaMap" border="0" />
		   
		   </div>

<map name="scaMap">
  <area shape ="rect" coords ="75,0,170, 55" href ="sca-interface.html" alt="Interface" />
  <area shape ="rect" coords ="410,0,505,55" href ="sca-interface.html" alt="Interface" />

  <area shape ="rect" coords ="75,222,160,308" href ="sca-binding.html" alt="Binding" />
  <area shape ="rect" coords ="425,222,511,308" href ="sca-binding.html" alt="Binding" />

  <area shape ="rect" coords ="245,222,330,308" href ="sca-implementation.html" alt="Implementation" />

  <area shape ="rect" coords ="108,178,130,187" href ="sca-wire.html" alt="Wire" />
  <area shape ="rect" coords ="280,178,305,187" href ="sca-wire.html" alt="Wire" />
  <area shape ="rect" coords ="455,178,480,187" href ="sca-wire.html" alt="Wire" />

  <area shape ="rect" coords ="145,105,260,170" href ="sca-component.html" alt="Component A" />
  <area shape ="rect" coords ="320,105,435,170" href ="sca-component.html" alt="Component B" />

  <area shape ="rect" coords ="0,105,105,170" href ="sca-service.html" alt="Service" />
  <area shape ="rect" coords ="475,105,580,170" href ="sca-reference.html" alt="Reference" />

  <area shape ="rect" coords ="245,0,307,22" href ="sca-property.html" alt="Property" />

  <area shape ="rect" coords ="60,60,525,215" href ="sca-composite.html" alt="Composite" />

</map>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
